this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net survey to
share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen
my guest today is lyron hymovic lyron is
the cto and co-founder of rook out
a production debugging company he's
active in the field of computer security
and an advocate of agile lean and devops
he is a frequent blogger and speaker
leron welcome to software engineering
radio hey robert it's great being here
leron and i are going to be talking
about customer issues escalated
to engineering
before we talk about escalation
let's talk about what is a customer
issue
so a customer issue can be a little bit
of everything i mean
whether it's an alert
going off in a in a production
monitoring system that showing something
might be wrong for a certain customer or
a group of customers
it can be a support ticket that the
customer opens it can be a feature
request it's in fact any indication that
either the customer is complaining or
asking for service all that something is
going wrong
and sometimes even obviously the walls
of those customer issues are those you
actually don't know about something went
wrong but you don't have the monitoring
all feedback loops in place to actually
understand that something has gone wrong
what is the business impact of issues on
the customer so working with our
customers we're seeing that
customer issues technical issues can
have a huge impact huge business impact
for them
and those can be different whether
you're a
sas company an on-prem solution provider
a b2b company a b2c company
but regardless of what sector you're on
we're seeing that customer issues have a
huge impact on the company's business
in the b2b sector we usually hear our
customers describe those issues are
helping their deal flow
whether it's a new deal or a new trial
that gets delayed or gets pushed back or
even lost to a competitor whether it's a
renewal or an upsell that goes that
becomes at risk
due to customer dissatisfaction due to
the issue
for b2c companies you often find in
those impact impacting the funnel
impacting conversion rates throughout
various flows of the panel impacting
customer satisfactions
nps calls referral rates and so on and
so forth and we've seen that almost no
matter what your business metrics are
customer issues and poor quality
can impact them
negatively
it must be very important then for
customers in any business
to be able to rely on the products and
services they use
do organizations typically offer any
kind of a guarantee about
how quickly issues will be addressed
so we're seeing that some customers try
to give those guarantees
i would say for the most part those
guarantees are very
defensive and lawyer likes
so you wouldn't those that you what you
tend to commit to
are
the very minimum the stuff you wouldn't
be able to
defend against in code rather than the
service you actually want to provide to
your customers usually we aim to provide
we every company i know aim to provide
the best service possible to their
customers resolving issues as fast as
possible and ensuring a smooth and
painless experience
while those guarantees those contractual
guarantees tend to be more about when
something is broken if you call us we'll
pick up the phone
but not necessarily once we pick up the
phone how fast are we going to help you
in any meaningful way you mentioned one
way that you learn about customer issues
your own internal monitoring system tell
you something is down or not working as
expected
if you learn about the issue from the
customer
how
does the customer communicate that to
the organization
so we're seeing customers communicate
issues to organizations in many
different ways
obvious ones are by contacting support
whether it's through in-app channels
in-app chats email addresses or phone
calls those are the obvious ones but
we're also seeing customers communicate
issues indirectly through product
reviews and application reviews in the
stalls through recommendations of these
recommendations on social networks blog
sites
and
we're even seeing that interactions
sometimes you can detect customer issues
as your metrics are suffering and
sometimes those metrics offering those
metrics going down mean that there is an
issue there is a bug that's hurting
preventing customers to convert as you
prefer essentially causing an issue
a customer issue then it's an issue
which is affecting the customer but
you're not necessarily learning about it
because the customer tells you there's a
lot of ways you might learn about it is
that right
i would say that generally speaking the
best way is to learn about the issue
before the customer even knows that
there is an issue
or at least before it tells you
and the second worst way to learn about
an issue is to have the customer tell
you the worst way to learn about the
issue after the customer is told other
people about it helping your reputation
what you don't want then is somebody
goes on social media and says i use this
product it's no good it's down all the
time
they suck
yeah that's the worst possible way i
mean
that's why you want to catch those
issues as fast as possible and resolve
them
as quickly as possible potentially even
proactively reaching out to your
customers where appropriate letting them
know that you've found and fix the
issues they've encountered so we're
going to be talking about customer
issues escalated to engineering what i
had in mind then
is that customer issues go somewhere
else and then they get escalated to
engineering what i've seen in most
organizations is alerts and monitoring
go directly to engineering so what are
the issues that do not go directly to
engineering where do they go so i would
say
so as you mentioned there are two major
kinds of customer issues the command
that you find yourself through alerts
monitoring and so on and the second is
the kind that comes from the customers
themselves by them letting us know that
there is a problem if the customer is
the one to contact us then usually it
goes to support or some other customer
facing sales like organization whether
it's support customer success account
management or whatnot
on the other hand
and we also think that when it comes to
technical alerts there can be many
different people who might actually get
that alert and it also depends on the
organizational structure you have itn
ops you sometimes have a devops
organization sometimes support is
partially responsible for operating
production
and
there are many other
stakeholders within the organization
that might be involved in the process of
identifying the issue prioritizing it
and determining what to do with it
let's talk about the customer facing
organizations that receive issue reports
directly from the customer
what is
the happy path for how these issues
would be addressed
so the happy path which
not many organizations are successful at
is that the whatever customer service
representative
is speaking with you is going to be
immediately able to identify your
problem fix it and send you happily on
your way
unfortunately that's rarely the case
and
quite often those customer service
representatives need additional support
additional knowledge additional
tools and then they gradually escalate
some of those issues to more qualified
personnel personnel have a deeper
understanding of the system
and quite often it goes all the way to
engineering
and the thing is those things that get
escalated to engineering
tend to have two things in common one is
that they tend to be very difficult to
solve because otherwise somebody else
should have been able to solve it
earlier and second that they're
important enough from business
perspective because if it's a small
problem even if we didn't manage to
solve it chances are it's going to get
de-prioritized
and only if it's something that's going
to have a real business impact will it
go escalate and get prioritized by the
product in management and so on and make
its way all the way to the other side of
the organization for engineering to take
a look at it and potentially fix it
is it often difficult to reproduce
issues that customers are reporting
i would say
from everything we've heard reproducing
issues is the biggest hurdle
reproducing customer issues is the
number one biggest problem engineers are
facing when they're trying to
tackle and resolve those problems even
worse it's not just about being able to
reproduce the issue it's about being
able to reproduce the issue reliably in
an environment you can control you can
observe you can understand
and unfortunately quite often the
production environment
doesn't have those characteristics
you've talked about the issues that
cannot be addressed immediately by the
customer facing organization are
escalated
who makes the call is this something
does the customer say i don't think i'm
getting anywhere with support i want
engineering or does customer facing say
this is out of our scope we need to get
engineering involved
so what we usually see is that a
customer-facing representative
say we can't solve this issue ourselves
and they try to
push it onwards escalating to somebody
who can help them
and unfortunately that's where
prioritization kicks in
because it's not just about what can be
resolved usually there are dozens
sometimes hundreds of issues
feature requests and ideas organizations
have to address on a daily basis
and yet
they can't resolve all of them
so once a set of issues that
can haven't been resolved properly by
the first deal support by the first year
of interaction with the customer is
identified then they are prioritized by
their impact on the customer by the
importance of the customer and the
overall business need of resolving them
i have heard some terminology in some
organizations where they have
multiple tiers
of support are those all tiered within
the customer facing organization or
is that more like
a priority or severity level that's
assigned
to the incident
and engineering may be involved in some
of the tiers
so what you usually see with customer
issues you see
there are kind of two
to access one is tears the other is
priorities now access is just one access
is a priority how important the issue is
it usually starts out with p0
ps0 means something horrible has
happened and the customer is unable to
use the system or even worse the
customer might be being limited in his
own ability to operate due to a failure
on our end
while a
p1 is a significant outage and p203 are
generally minor outages or just feature
requests so that's kind of the priority
side of the things and those keep in
mind those priorities are per customer
so something might be p0 for the least
important customer of the company where
something else might be p2 but it's
going to be for the most important comp
any customer in the company so they
might be treated differently and it's
not just about a
customer priority it's also about the
business priority
so i may have conflated a couple
different things there the tiering of
issues with the severity and the
priority
yeah and now tiers are essentially
the expertise level the experience of
whoever is dealing with the system
smaller organizations are going to have
one or two tiers one large organization
may have as many as four or five
and with the usually tier one and tier
two residing within this customer facing
organization customer support customer
success whatever
while a tier three tier four might live
within operations or engineering well
tier 4 sometimes tier 5 refers to
engineering itself
the higher tiers are engineers who have
a deep experience in the product who are
potentially able to solve any issue with
the product or at least identify the
cause exactly
all engineering
teams have some process for getting work
into their system whether they have
scrums or planning or project planning
what is the process where customer
facing
identifies work that they want
engineering to do and how does that get
into the engineering workload
so in some ways it's the same new
essentially
the organization has some processes in
place to
align all the stakeholders
and kind of get everything on board kind
of saying whether it's based on a
pre-allocated
set of resources that are dedicated for
support whether it's by
reducing the scope of the roadmap
temporarily so they do unplanned work
instead of planned work
and it's a bit of balance
now
many of us kind of know how tricky it is
and how complex it is to align on the
long-term product roadmap because
everybody wants a piece everybody has a
feature that's the most important for
them and
everybody's kind of speaking from their
own organizational positioning about
what's important what's not in many ways
prioritizing support issues is even
worse
it's worse because people actually have
a real
personal stake in it not only because
different people are responsible for
different accounts and for the accounts
that are responsible they care deeply
about and they very well know
they also care personally about the
people they are working with in most
organizations customer facing
representatives are compensated based on
their ability to deliver value to the
customers so essentially once a customer
comes with a bug
that may change the business impact that
customer the team working on that from
the business side of things might
actually have their compensation
affected by whether or not this bug is
resolved and by how much now obviously
as you can imagine people are much more
emotional and much more personally
invested when their compensation is on
the line by whether or not a bug is
solved
now in addition to the personal
compensation
the other thing that's different from
traditional roadmap prioritization
is the time span
when working on a roadmap you have a
fairly long schedule whether you're
working in weeks or months or sometimes
even years
it's something that's a bit long longer
term and easier to
take time to make your decisions take
time to deliver and so on and so forth
when it comes to support
usually everything is for tomorrow it's
not yesterday everything is overdue and
by definition the customer is already
unhappy because something has gone wrong
and so this urgency
drives the process much faster drives at
a much higher volume of discussion
and
drives in general tensions are much much
higher when it comes to support
every organization has
competing uses for its scarce resources
somewhere at some level of management
has to decide
we're either going to build new products
or support the ones we have
or make the ones we have better
help the customers
how is an organization deciding
how to prioritize customer issues in the
mix
so i guess the answer it depends
it depends on whether power centers
within the organization lies is the
organization engineering driven is it
product driven is it marketing driven is
it sales driven is it somewhere else
whoever is driving has the most capital
in the organization
is gonna have a biggest impact on that
usually you see that in sales driven
organizations for instance customer
issues are the most important things
because they have a direct impact
short-term impact on the bottom line
while organization focusing more on
engineering culture might not care as
much
about individual customers and
individual customer issues
and so it depends a lot
and also obviously decision making
processes change from organization to
organization it's data driven is it
driven by personality driven by whoever
is pushing it forward is it driven by
other elements it can differ very
greatly
you mentioned a few minutes ago the idea
of unplanned work do most customer
issues fall into the category of
unplanned work
definitely as
i'm sure you know
and we generally
divide engineering tasks into planned
and unplanned work and planned walk is
everything you mentioned on the roadmap
side and new features upgrades to system
and so on and so forth and unplanned
walk with everything we can't exactly
predict ahead but know that's going to
happen
i would say customer issues are
definitely the biggest and most painful
type of unplanned walk for most of
organizations we've seen it is the most
business impact on the short term it's
the ones the most guaranteed to happen
and so it's a huge driver
and unfortunately it's even harder to
predict
and not only
what's the issue going to be but which
teams are going to be involved in
what is the impact of unplanned work on
the planned work things like your
roadmap
so obviously that's going to be a huge
impact being able to
pre-allocate unplanned work versus
planned walk
has a big impact it's a huge impact on
the ability to plan
and what you're going to do how your
roadmap is going to look like
and unfortunately
it can be tricky the more you are able
to
predict unplanned work the more you are
able to categorize it ahead of time and
allocate specific resources to it
the better it is
and one of i think the most important
thing is
how well can you handle that unplanned
walks when it comes in
is it throwing all your plans away are
you trying to relearn the system relearn
the tools re-educate the team
or do you have a procedure in place you
have the tools in place to tackle those
issues as they come because you've
already seen dozens of them and you kind
of know what's going to be coming up
next down the road what would that look
like what kind of procedure would you
put in place
so each organization has though
different types of
unplanned walk in general and customer
issues in particular sometimes
let's say a customer is reporting a bug
in your backend application you're going
to need a certain set of tools to be
able to investigate that you're going to
want some level of
observability into the performance of
the application such as an apm
especially if you're suffering from
performance issues on a regular basis
you're gonna want some level of logging
you need to be able to understand
at least briefly what the customer was
doing when something went wrong and
you'll probably want to be able to give
your team a set of tools that will allow
them to see information about the
customer access the customer profile and
so on and so forth which can be a bit
tricky in production environments due to
security and privacy concerns
and last but not least you definitely
want a tool that will allow your
engineers the ability to
extract additional data
as they learn they need it
rather than having to
spend a lot of engineering cycles and
efforts on data collection just to
resolve issues you're talking about
extracting additional data are you
talking about
telemetry that you could say increase
log levels
of logs that you've already instrumented
your code or in other ways crank up the
level of telemetry
to collect more data
about what's happening or more finely
targeted
exactly we need to think of
observability in general as an agile
platform we can't just
stick ourselves with a very strict very
rigid set of pieces of data
and rely on that same piece of data day
in day out to save us because we're
going to be getting many different
issues and each of them is going to
require different insights now stuff
such as a increasing log velocity for
specific models or users stuff such as
being able to insert new log lines
on the fly
and all that those are critical elements
that are going to allow your engineering
teams
to collect data faster
to adapt the data they are collecting to
the issue that are handling at hand
rather than trying to collect everything
all the time
which is not going to work and it's
probably going to cost you a fortune as
well in observability tools
i think what you're talking about is
if you've built one or two products
you're aware that there are going to be
issues that you get out in front of that
by saying let's engineer into products
from day one
the ability
to do the tasks that we know are going
to need to do
to resolve the issue so it's already
there rather than
waiting until you have an issue and then
asking how do we figure out what's going
on yeah so we definitely need to design
our systems
to be able to collect data from them and
we definitely need to take our insights
from the past from previous projects
from the teams experience to build a
system that's easy to troubleshoot
and but we also need to find a way to
build agility into the system and i know
that's what we're doing at rookout by by
building agility into the observability
of the system you can adapt the data
you're collecting whether you need new
metrics new logs whether you just need
to know what's available value somewhere
being able to use agile telemetry
makes a huge impact in your ability to
get the data you need when you need it
rather than trying to walk around
the data you happen to have
and trying to
figure out how to make the conclusions
you need from random data that was
decided upon in the past could you tell
me a story of an issue that you were
involved in that got escalated
and how the engineering team approached
it so i have dozens of stories i think
one of my favorites was actually one of
the first customers we deployed rook of
that they had a
an internal a
portal for employees to actually report
id outages
and a handful of employees were unable
to log into that portal everybody else
were successful in logging into that
portal but that specific a handful of
people couldn't have been logged in
and they've actually been chasing that
bug for over six months
trying to figure out what's wrong and
essentially whenever those people came
into the application they were asked to
log in via their google account they
logged in and then essentially after the
screen kept refreshing and it got stuck
and then they got an error message
now using rook out the team kind of
followed down that rabbit hole trying to
see what's going on
and it turned out that when they were
using the google api for logging in
they've actually passed the flag saying
provides us with the full profile within
the jwt and the json web token that was
used for authentication then and when
they got the jwt back they did a set of
a sanity test on it and one of those
sanity tests was actually testing for
that for the size
of the string and if the string was too
long i think about over 8000 characters
then they would trim it down to 8 000
characters
and unfortunately as it was assigned
ajwt for those people for those handful
of people their profiles were larger the
jwt which the profile got packed into
jwt it was larger and then this token
got trimmed
essentially pushing the system into a
re-login loop that ended up with an
infinite redirect loop terminated by the
browser now the irony is within that if
a string longer than 8000 characters
they actually add a comment
at the log line here this should never
happen at the log line here
and that log line was never added
and i think that's a perfect example
that we can't always rely on the
observability decisions that were made
when the code was written
obviously there is there is going to be
plethora of knowledge a huge amount of
knowledge in those in that whether it's
a information level logging debug level
logging metrics and so on and so forth
and we want to be able to access all of
that but we also need the ability to
adapt
observability on the fly to collect new
data
as new facts come to light
sometimes we are debugging code that's
you know it's the most of the code where
debugging wasn't written last week maybe
it was written a year ago or a decade
ago
and we need the ability to easily
reinstrument it and collect new data
as we're dealing with new challenges
today's sponsor is spot by netapp the
cloud automation platform that makes it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
infrastructure at the lowest possible
cost
get the most out of your cloud
investments by automating cloud
infrastructure to ensure performance
reduce complexity and optimize costs
their machine learning and automation
scale to exactly meet application needs
using the most efficient mix of
instances and pricing models eliminating
the risks of over provisioning and cloud
waste
leverage spot with all leading cloud
platform services and tools
check them out at spot.io
se radio where you can find more
information request a demo or even start
a free trial
[Music]
you mentioned people chasing that issue
around for six months is that a
unusual amount of time
to resolve an issue
so i would say it's not your average bug
most bugs do get resolved within a
few days maybe two or three weeks
and once i actually get walked on but
almost every team i've met with
including i have my own personal horror
stories everybody i know has a set of
bugs they've
chased for six months or more
some people i've met have bugs they've
chased for over a year and still haven't
solved
and those bugs just by noticing that
people have kept walking in it for six
months
means they were important they were
somebody cared about them and still they
couldn't get them resolved within a
reasonable time frame when an issue is
open that long is it the same person
who's trying different things or is the
issue passed around
among different people or maybe even
different teams
so usually you would see those issues
get passed around so if that issue is
important enough to be worked on you
would definitely want additional people
to get started with it
at the very least you would want a
couple of more people from the same team
to take a look
but definitely is a organizations are
often very big
you would find that a single bug can
involve
three or five or seven teams and then
you quite often have 20 or 30 people all
involved in trying to chase down that
bug
and that's tough in some email we you
and i exchanged
before
podcast you mentioned
the
drain that issues create on development
resources i can totally see that from
this story you're talking about
in particular mentioned issues with
technical debt and employee motivation
could you go more into that
of course so
technical debt
is
a loaded term that can mean many things
essentially the bottom line i would say
is that whoever saying something is
technical that
they're saying they don't like
how whatever is
being written whether it's a component
or an application or whatnot
how that
application is being built and how it's
operating right now and there can be
many many reasons for why somebody
doesn't like how something is built i
would say the obvious tool is that
something was built
very poorly or that something was built
in a way that you know difference of
opinions that whoever wrote it
originally and over is working on it now
and failed to agree on how it should be
done
but for most part those are actually i
would say the
the real the rare stuff those are the
less common stuff the two most common
reasons we're seeing for technical debt
one that something has been adopted
to walk differently something started
out with certain function and gradually
over time moved to something else
which means that obviously it's not
doing whatever it's doing right now very
good because it was never meant to do
that
and two which is even more common
is that people are saying something is
technical debt
because they fail to understand it they
don't have a good enough
good enough understanding of what's
going on why is it going on why it was
designed that way and so they
kind of due to lack of understanding
they don't like what they're saying they
don't understand it they think it could
be done better and quite often once
people truly understand how something
was written and why it was written then
they don't hate it as much they don't
consider it as much technical debt and
obviously dealing with customer issues
is
a great example of that because somebody
is complaining the code is not operating
properly
and
how well do you understand the code how
well it was designed to do whatever it's
doing those are critical terms in your
ability to
understand and more importantly fix the
issue
so when we're trying to tie together
technical debt and customer issues are
you saying that the customer issues
reveal that the company for example did
not invest enough in
design or testing or monitoring when the
product was shipped and that's why we're
seeing the issue now
i wouldn't go as far as saying that
sometimes
customer issues are unavoidable no
matter the only way to avoid customer
issues is to not have customers
which is not a good strategy at least
for most of us at the same time we have
to prepare ahead of time we have to
think through it we do have to to do our
best to design the product properly to
test it properly to bring it to the
highest quality we can provide
while still delivering it fast enough
and delivering value to the customer and
to the organization
however it's also important to
note that customer issues especially
repeated customer issues significant
customer issues are usually a sign that
something is wrong usually a sign of
technical debt and that technical debt
might be because the code is bad or has
been misused
but it can also be that we've kind of
shifted away from the code or that the
team doesn't have as good in the grasp
of the code as it used to and so they're
making modifications that are
inadvertently adding bugs to the code
and so throughout the process you kind
of have to
it's all about empowering your engineers
to
learn the code to understand it the best
possible way
and also kind of
avoid too much of emotional resonance
focus on the code focus on the technical
part focus on the professionalism
and if there is a problem with the code
if it's being modified if it needs to be
written which is often the crusade for
every engineer who's claiming technical
debt like the crusade is obviously
rewrite it refactor it rebuild it
sometimes that's needed oftentimes it's
not
but i think the most important fact when
dealing with technical debt is first and
foremost understand the code understand
the design understand what's going on
and once you've got that
visibility make sure you have the
tooling in place to keep it high quality
and think about testing and so on and so
forth
the other area you mentioned
unplanned work from customer issues
being very impactful is employee
motivation
what did you mean by that
so engineers like building new new shiny
stuff or at least most engineers
and nothing is
more remote from building new shutting
stuff
then
we're fixing customer issues
that's essentially kind of you know
trading in place
going day in day out and
making sure that something's that's
supposed to be working is working
and that's there is very little
satisfaction very little feeling of
progress in that even worse while you
are kind of
trying to fix something that should be
fixed the children will already be
working
you're encountering two additional
issues the first is that quite often you
have very little understanding of what's
going on what's the problem when are you
going to figure out what's the problem
and when are you going to fix it so
you're essentially in the dark
and even more so you are under a lot of
pressure because as we mentioned there
might there is a business impact on the
line it's a very short term
and quite often many important people in
the organizations are going to care
about the business impact
and so sometimes you're going to have
a lot of people breathing down your neck
about when is this going to be resolved
how can you go faster and so on and so
forth while you don't even know what's
going on
and so the ability to collect data
to understand what's going on to
is paramount in your ability to feel in
control
and deliver faster and
avoid the motivation
yeah i could see if you
feel like you're doing the same thing
over and over again and work you thought
you shipped
keeps coming back to you it could be
very demotivating but on the other hand
i had a conversation with an engineer
recently who's in
ops or support he said he realized at an
early point his curry wasn't very good
at building things but if something
broke he was very good at fixing it
quickly do you think there's a type of
person where they get joy and
satisfaction out of chasing down
problems and solving them
there is definitely joy
in chasing down problems and solving
them
i think aware of that joy is more fun
it's more glamorous it's more
enjoyable
when you're dealing with new stuff
that you're fixing a problem
that wasn't there before you you're
building something new you found a
problem you're fixing it now something
is new is working and it's not as
enjoyable
when you're dealing with something that
should already have been working so
essentially delivering something new is
going you know from the bottom to up
while fixing something it should already
be walking it's kind of
top to bottom and back to the top
which is not nearly as much fun so we've
talked a lot about what kind of problems
go to support how they're solved the
need to be
proactive in how you build the product
so that you have these tools to do
telemetry when you have a problem you
can be productive in getting data to
chase it down are there overall some
best practices for an organization
you also mentioned you're going to have
customer issues so
we don't live in a world where you can
say we'll ship it it'll be perfect we
won't have any issues so we don't need
to plan for that what are the best
practices for organization to
effectively
be able to handle these issues so
there are a few key concepts here the
first is to acknowledge that you're
gonna have those customer issues it's
paramount that you know that you're
gonna have them
and you need to set expectations you
need to set expectations with the
product team that you're gonna need to
allocate some resources for unplanned
work you need to set expectations with
the business team and sometimes with the
customer himself that there are gonna be
issues
but you're gonna be there and you're
gonna fix those issues as fast as you
can and you need to set expectations
with the engineering team
to make sure that they know that once
they've delivered the new feature they
have to be there to support it they have
to be there to solve the customer issues
around it number two you need to
define a clear process
we've talked about a bit early on how
those issues are going to be coming in
are they going to be coming in from
alerts or they're going to coming in
from bugs from bug reports who is going
to be picking them up who is going to be
decide what's important what's not
and that process you you probably want
some draft early on and you want to
gradually walk on it and improve on it
as you're seeing thing through and you
definitely want to empower your
engineers number three you want to
empower your team
you definitely want to make sure your
engineers have the touring place
to
investigate those issues
so first of you want some observability
tools second you probably want some
back-office stores that are going to
provide your engineers some insight into
the profiles of the customers and the
configuration of the system and so on
and third you want to empower your teams
to agilely collect data whether you're
using ci cd whether you're using rook
out you need to make sure that your
engineers are going to have the tools to
push new data collection and you want
those tools to be effective you want
them to be secure efficient
and you don't want your engineers stuck
on missing data because that's the
number one problem most of the times
your engineers are going to be solved
trying to find a bug rather than
directly fix it and the one thing they
need to find bugs is information
last but not least you want to improve
throughout the process
we've talked about various parts of the
process how do you get the bugs how do
you prioritize them who is involved how
do you fix them how do you collect data
observability and so on and so forth you
want
to learn from the process you want to
learn
about what kind of bugs are coming in
how can you fix them faster which bugs
took you i know two months six months
how can you make sure they are not going
to take you that long next time
and keep in mind that you can often use
those customer issues as feedback for
the product team for the engineering
team on how to build a better product
and how to empower your support team to
resolve more issues themselves next time
could you give an example of something
you learned from dealing with customer
issues enabled you to improve how
the place where you worked which could
be rook out or someplace that enabled
you to improve how the organization
handled customer issues
sure so at workout we provide sdks for
remote debugging and data collection and
we provide them for five languages for a
java.net
ruby python node
and early on we started deploying i
think it was java for the first time
we had a lot of learning curve every
time we went to a customer
and we wanted to deploy the sdk
we kind of we ran into various issues
and we on the one hand we used every one
of those issues to improve the product
to make it easier to deploy to make it
more stable and so on at the same time
we've also built out the questionnaire
so we've built out a questionnaire that
has all those key elements that we know
we want to learn before we get started
with the customers whether it's our java
versions their operating system
or many other and what cloud they're on
whatever it is and we've now we've built
that question new we can share with
customers we can share with our support
team with engineering team and whenever
we're dealing with the customers we make
sure we have that data
and we want the data before deployment
we want that data available whenever bug
is reported and so we are much more
focused
when we're working on those customer
issues because we know what we're facing
and throughout the process we've
learned time after time
how not only to resolve the direct
issues we're encountering but also to
where the product needs to be redesigned
to be more reliable to be easier to use
and to be safer
and you can see the impact
a huge impact on how quickly and safely
the product can be installed today
versus it was a few years ago the
difference was between having this data
and not having it and by having it
you're able to drive
more rapid resolution of issues
okay and even sometimes even detect them
before the customer because we know what
to look for and what to test and so on
so forth
organizations invest a lot of resources
in
building new products and ensuring the
quality of the products they have things
different types of testing
we've also talked about you can't avoid
customer issues you need to plan
to handle them and to handle them
efficiently do you have any thoughts on
how do you decide whether you have too
many issues and the best path is you
need to do a better job
at handling them or you need to invest
more
in quality up front so you don't have as
many what's the balance where you should
invest
that's a difficult question that's a
good question i would say that
first foremost if you're not seeing any
issues
then something is wrong maybe you don't
have customers or more likely you don't
have a good enough feedback loop because
chances are there are issues
and you're just they're flying below the
radar
and it's you probably want to improve
your feedback look better monitoring
better customer communication learn more
about the issues
on the other hand you shouldn't be
overly worried
about having too many issues
because if you dig in deep enough if you
communicate enough with the customers
there are going to be endless issues
there is always room to improve and
there are many matters of opinion and
many things that might be going outside
the realm of the specification of the
system or the performance of the system
and you shouldn't be overly concerned
with
having issues or even the number of the
issues
what you do need to think about is are
those issues impacting the business
our customers satisfied with their
product or not
the customer is satisfied with the
quality
in many cases you have very clear slas
very clear expectations some products
have to be up for 99 of the times while
others have to be up for 99.99
nine percent of the time so-called five
nines
and based on the category you're in
based on your customers you should have
some clear understanding
of what's the business value of uptime
for instance of quality
and what threshold you're aiming for
and then you need to measure yourself
against the threshold am i meeting the
five nines criteria our customers
enjoying my product our customers
complaining about the quality of the
product because customers might be
reporting issues on the one hand you
might have tons of bugs but if you at
the same time they might be very happy
with the quality because you know if you
have enough customers and everybody's
complaining about minitia and small
stuff they don't care about they might
still be happy
loren
do you have any final thoughts
on the topic that we haven't covered no
that's pretty much it
okay
where would people find rook out if they
want to know something about it so feel
free to reach out to us at rookout.com
and you can also find me on twitter
liran
we'll put that in underscore
show notes
leron thank you very much for speaking
to software engineering radio thanks
robert for having me thanks everybody
for listening in this has been robert
blumen for software engineering radio
and thank you for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening